Guide to the James G. McDonald Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series II: General Correspondence, 1914-1962
  - Lewisohn, Samuel and Mrs., 1930-1949 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Long, Breckenridge, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Lourie, Arthur, 1934-1960 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Lucas, Scott W., 1948 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Ma-Mc (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Marks, Sir Simon, 1946-1960 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - May, Herbert L. 1932-1934, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Mazer Family (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - McDonald, Edward D., 1923-1960 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - McDonald, Anna, 1924-1934 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - McDonald Family (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - McDonald, James G.
    - Biography (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Personal Finances (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Automobile Insurance (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 75th Birthday (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Memorabilia (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - McDonald, John A., 1928-1934 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - McDonald, Joseph Lee, 1922-1961 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - McDonald, William H.,1922-1961 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - McGhee, George C., 1949-1951 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Me-Mz (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Mead, James M., 1945-1946 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Merz, Charles, 1939-1957 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Messersmith, George S., 1933-1947 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Phillips, William, 1933-1959 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Millin, Sarah Gertrude, 1948-1949 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Minton, Sherman, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Montor, Henry, 1947-1958 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Moses, Robert, 1953-1958 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Murray, Thomas E., 1956-1948 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - N (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Myers-Henderson Case, 1930 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Nathan, Otto, 1934-1936 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - New York Times (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - New York University (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - New York University Project (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Niles, David K., 1943-1951 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Norman, Edward A., 1937-1945 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - O (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - P (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Padberg, Eugene L., Jr., 1950-1951 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Parkes, James W., 1933-1959 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Parsons, Geoffrey, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Passport Division, Dept of State (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Pervy, Adolphe, 1936-1961 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Peurifoy, John E., 1950 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Phillips, David, 1954-1959 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Picon, Molly, 1953-1954 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Q (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Ra-Rof (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Ra-Rof (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Rabinowitz, Louis M., 1951-1955 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Radio Advisory Board (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Refugee Rehabilitation Committee (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Refugees--Appeal for Funds (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Rifkind, Simon H. 1946-1953 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Riley, William E., 1948-1953 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Robinson, Leland Rex, 1931-1961 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Rog-Rz (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Rogosin, Israel, 1955-1960 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Rokach, Israel, 1948-1951 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Rothberg, Sam, 1950-1960 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Rountree, William M., 1946-1959 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Rusk, Dean, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Russell, Francis H., 1954 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Russian War Relief, Inc. (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Rycus, Jacob, 1952-1954 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Sa-Schu (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Salant, Richard S., 1948-1959 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Sarnoff, Irving, 1951, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Satterthwaite, Joseph, 1948-1949 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Sawyer, Olive L., 1952-1960 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Sayre, Francis B., 1936-1947 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Schw-Sh (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Schwartz, Joseph J., 1952-1961 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Seeve, Harry, 1952-1955 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Senate Committees, Armed Services and Foreign Relations (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Sharett, Moshe, 1950-1960 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Si-Sp (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Silver, Edward S., 1954-1960 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Slawson, John, 1948-1960 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Sloan, Alfred P., Jr., 1942-1945 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Smith, H. Alexander, 1933-1952 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Synder, John W., 1946 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Sobeloff, Simon E., 1952-1955 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Sokolsky, George, 1953 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Spain, King and Queen of (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - St-Sz (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Stone, William T.,1927-1953 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Sugrue, Thomas, 1949-1953 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Swig, Benjamin, 1952-1961 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - T (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Travel
    - Israel, Spain (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Australia, Far East (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - South America (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Europe and Israel (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Israel (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Europe, 1933 (2 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Europe, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Europe, 1931 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Addresses (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Trujillo, Rafael L., 1953-1954 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Twentieth Century Fund (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - U (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Uhlmann, Paul, 1950-1960 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - University of Miami (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - V (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Van Tijn, Gertrude, 1951-1959 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Vardi, Itzhak, 1954 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Vassar College (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Wa-We (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Waller, Frederic Elton, 1952-1961 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Warren, George L., 1953-1954 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Weinstein, Joe, 1948-1960 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - WH-Wz (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Wheeler, Burton K., 1945 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Winchell, Walter, 1951 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Wise, Jonah B., 1949-1954 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Wyzanski, Charles E. Jr., 1934-1955 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - X-Y (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Z (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Zionist Organization of America (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Zionist Organization of America--Proofs, undated (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Zylberlast, Henry and Sonia, 1956-1959 (Box 20, Folder 11)
- Series III: Manuscripts and Speeches, 1914-1960
  This series holds drafts of two of McDonald's books, Palestine and the Middle East and My Mission to Israel, as well as drafts and transcripts of his speeches on current events and international policy. It includes many of the speeches McDonald broadcast over radio while working for the Foreign Policy Association, drafts for a 1943 NBC radio show, and many other speeches given before a variety organizations. Materials are arranged chronologically.
  - General, 1914-1921 (5 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 12 to 16)
  - Speeches, 1922-1943 (15 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 1 to 15)
  - Radio Scripts (NBC), 1943 (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 16 to 17)
  - Radio Scripts (NBC), 1943 (4 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 1 to 4)
  - Speeches, 1945-1946 (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Palestine in the Middle East, Part I (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Palestine in the Middle East, Part II,III, IV, (4 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 1 to 4)
  - Speeches, 1947-1950 (4 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 5 to 8)
  - My Mission to Israel
    - Chapters 1-35 (2 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Chapters 36-52 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Page Proofs,1951 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Galley Proofs (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Simon & Schuster Contract Material (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Lists for Publicity (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Distribution, 1950-1952 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Speeches, 1951-1953 (3 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 7 to 9)
  - Speeches, 1954-1960 (6 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 1 to 6)
  - Notes, undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - British Guiana Reports (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - McDonald, James G. "What Should Be America's Policy in the Far East?" 1937 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - State Department (Box 33, Folder 6)
- Series IV: High Commissioner for Refugees, 1933-1936
  This series contains material relating to League's effort to help refugees attempting to leave Germany prior to World War II. It includes reports from meetings with Nazi officials and extensive letters and reports discussing the insurance and property rights of refugees. Several files document McDonald's trip to South America with S.G. Inman to assess potential locations for refugee settlements. Documents are arranged chronologically.
  - McDonald Resignation (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Confidential File, 1933-1934 (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 9 to 10)
  - Confidential File, 1934-1936 (3 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Finances and Expenses, 1933-1935 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Geneva Office, 1933-1934 (5 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 5 to 9)
  - Geneva Office, 1934-1935 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Statement of Resignation and Drafts, 1935 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Inman, S.G.
    - Correspondence, 1934-1936 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Interviews, 1935 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Inman-McDonald Missions South America, 1935 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Inman-McDonald Missions--Central and South America Duplicates (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Kotschnig, Walter M., 1936 (2 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 2 to 3)
  - National Coordinating Comm, New York, Cecilia Razovsky (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1936 Olive L., Sawyer (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Wurfbain, Andre L., 1936 (2 Folders) (Box 29, Folder 6 to 7)
  - Lists and Organizations, 1933-1935 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Speeches and Releases, 1933-1936 (2 Folders) (Box 30, Folder 2 to 3)
  - Clippings (Box 30, Folder 4)
- Series V: Presidential Advisory Committee on Political Refugees, 1936-1945
  Series V is comprised of a wide range of documents on refugee issues, including discussions of visa requirements; letters from groups seeking to help particular groups of refugees (such as children or Spanish refugees); and correspondence on technical problems, such as transportation issues. Files are arranged alphabetically by name or topic.
  - Clippings--German Newspapers, 1938 (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1936 (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Food Map, 1938 (Box 48, Folder 9)
  - A-B (2 Folders) (Box 30, Folder 5 to 6)
  - Bentwich, Norman, 1940 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - C-D (2 Folders) (Box 30, Folder 8 to 9)
  - D'Avigdor-Goldsmid, Sir Osmond E, 1939 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Dominican Republic Settlement, 1942 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - E (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Evian Conference, 1938 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Evian Conference--Clippings 1938 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - F (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Ford Conference, 1941 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - G (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - H (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Harrison, Earl G., 1945 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - I (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - "International Understanding and Friendship"--Article, 1936 (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - J-K (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 12 to 13)
  - Kotschnig, Walter M., 1938-1939 (Box 31, Folder 14)
  - L-M (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 15 to 16)
  - May, Herbert L., 1939-1940 (Box 31, Folder 17)
  - Mexico (Box 31, Folder 18)
  - N-P (3 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 19 to 21)
  - Palestine-Partition, 1936-1938 (Box 31, Folder 22)
  - Refugee Economic Corp. (Box 31, Folder 23)
  - R (Box 31, Folder 24)
  - Robinson, Leland Rex, 1943 (Box 31, Folder 25)
  - Rosenberg, James N., 1938-1939 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Rosenwald, William, 1942 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Rummel, Joseph, 1938-1945 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - S (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Schenkolewski, M., 1940-1944 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Strauss, Lewis L., 1938-1941 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - T (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Twentieth Century Fund,1939 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - U-W (3 Folders) (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Warren, George L., 1938-1941 (6 Folders) (Box 32, Folder 12 to 17)
  - Warren, George L., 1943-1945 (3 Folders) (Box 33, Folder 1 to 3)
- Series VI: Photographs, 1937-1961
  This series holds a small number of photographs of McDonald, primarily formal portraits.
  - McDonald, James C., undated (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Bleakley, William and James G., McDonald, undated (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - McDonald, James G., 1938-1961 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - McDonald, James G., undated (2 Folders) (Box 33, Folder 10 to 11)
  - Ben-Gurion, David and James G. McDonald, undated (Box 33, Folder 12)
- Series VII: Development Corporation For Israel, 1951-1961
  This small series contains business documents from McDonald's position as chairman of the Advisory Council. It includes correspondence, meeting information, speaking schedules, and expense reports.
  - Abrams, Benjamin, 1952-1953 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1953-1961 (9 Folders) (Box 34, Folder 2 to 10)
  - Speaking Schedule, 1951-1955 (5 Folders) (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Speaking Schedule, 1956-1961 (7 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 1 to 7)
  - Expense Accounts, 1951-1956 (6 Folders) (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Expense Accounts, 1957-1961 (5 Folders) (Box 36, Folder 1 to 5)
- Series VIII: Pamphlets and Clipping Books, 1914-1951
  - Subseries I: Pamphlets, 1914-1951
    This subseries holds pamphlets containing McDonald's articles on refugees and Palestine. They are filed chronologically.
    - "German 'Atrocities' and International Law," 1914 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - "The German Refugees and the League of Nations," 1936 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - "International Broadcasting--A Humanizing Force," 1933 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Letter of Resignation of James G. McDonald (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - "Palestine: The Primary Hope of the Post-War Era," 1945 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - "Palestine to the Rescue: Life or Death Struggle for a People," undated (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - "Should the United States Open Its Doors to Displaced Persons Now?" 1946 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - "The Truth About Palestine," 1946 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - "What is Happening to Christian Spiritual Values in Today's World?" 1951 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - "What is the Best Solution to the Palestine Problem?", 1947 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - "Where can the Refugees Go?" 1945 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Stefansky, George, "Does the Refugee Have a Future" (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II: Clipping Books, 1921-1939
    This subseries is comprised of newspaper articles about Poletti's actions as chairman of the Foreign Policy Association, League of Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, and chairman of the President’s Advisory Commission on Political Refugees. Clippings are arranged chronologically.
    - Clipping Book, 1921-1929 (3 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 4 to 6)
    - Clipping Book, 1929-1931 (2 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 7 to 8)
    - Clipping Books, 1931-1933 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Clipping Book, 1931-1933 (2 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Clipping Book, 1932-1936 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Clipping Book, 1936-1939 (Box 37, Folder 4)
- Series IX: Research Files, 1838-1956
  This series holds research information on nine topics: civil rights, communism, constitutional amendments, immigration, McCarthyism, the Refugee Relief Act, senate rules, tidelands, and Vietnam. Files for each topic contain a variety of clippings, letters, memos, and pamphlets, as well as McDonald's notes and note cards. Files are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Civil Rights
    - Army Education Segregation--W.B.W. Personal File, 1956 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Army and Education I: University of South Carolina, 1949-1956 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Army and Education II, undated (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Background Material, 1951-1956 (3 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Discharge of H.R. (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Economic Coercion (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - Election Statistics (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Fair Employment Practices Commission (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - Housing Discrimination (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Communism, 1955 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Constitutional Amendment
    - Bricker Amendment, 1952-1955 (3 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 2 to 4)
    - Lodge-Gossett,1940-1955 (2 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - S.J. Res. No. 3 "Relative to the Taking of Private Property,"1953-1954 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Eastland, James O., Background material, 1956 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Immigration
    - Amendments in 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Bibliography, 1953 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - Crime Statistics, 1952-1954 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - Draft Speeches (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - Editorials, 1953 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Foreign Press Comments, 1952-1953 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - General Articles, 1952-1953 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Hardship Cases, 1953 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Hate Literature, 1953 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Hate Literature, pre-1953 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Human Interest Background, 1952-1953 (Box 42, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Justice Department: Deportations, 1953-1955 (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - McCarran Bill: Amendment to S.2550 1952 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - McCarran Bill Fact Sheet For Floor Debate (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Private Bills, 1953 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Publications and Reprints, 1952-1953 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Race, 1953 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Resolutions and Editorials in Congressional Record, 1953 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Statistics, 1953-1954 (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Illegal Immigrants, 1954 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Illegal Immigrants, pre-1954 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - McCarthyism
    - McCarthy, Joseph
      - Background Material, 1950-1953 (Box 44, Folder 3)
      - Censure, 1950-1954 (Box 44, Folder 4)
      - Charges Against McCarthy by Lehman (Box 44, Folder 5)
      - Lehman Franking Controversy, 1953-1954 (Box 44, Folder 6)
      - Lehman Franking Controversy, 1953-1954 (Box 45, Folder 1)
      - Lehman's Resolution, 1949-1953 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Refugee Relief Act
    - Refugee Relief Act (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Amendments and Hearings I, 1955-1956 (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Amendments and Hearings II, 1954 (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Monthly Report of Assurances, 1954-1956 (Box 45, Folder 6)
    - Status of Visa Applications per Week, 1955-1956 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Senate Rules
    - Fair Procedures I, 1950-1954 (2 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Senate Conference Reports, 1954 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Tidelands
    - Background Material I (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Background Material II: Historical Content 1838-1936 (2 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Foreign Waters (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - General Material, 1953-1955 (3 Folders) (Box 47, Folder 2 to 4)
    - General Material, 1945, 1948, 1950, 1952 (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam, 1954 (Box 47, Folder 4)